Guide to the Department of Agricultural Economics Research Project Records 1911-1963
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
- Flathead Cream Marketing, 1953-1954; 22
  Forms for Flathead County dairy farms including farmers' names, dairy sales distribution, and seasonal variation
  - Flathead Cream Marketings, 1953-1954 (Box 10, Folder 35)
- Deadman Basin Project (Irrigation) and others, 23
  Provides information on operator names, investment costs, irrigation development and drainage costs, pasture development, reservoirs, dugouts, springs, wells, irrigation history, cattle, sheep, other livestock and products, machinery, labor, taxes, grazing, crop production and use.
  - Deadman Basin Project (Irrigation) and others (Box 10, Folder 36-39)
- Blackfeet Ranching Study, 24
  Includes data concerning crops, pasture, non-farm income, loans, grazing practices, calf crop, cattle, sheep, swine, land valuation, ownership and land use, irrigated range and farmland, land tenure and production, rangeland cut for hay and value, family organization and farm-livestock practices, expenses, and livestock tabulation.
  - Blackfeet Ranching Study (Box 10, Folder 40-41)
- Craig Ranch Study, 1942; 25
  Provides information related to Glen Craig's ranch study in the form of letters, budgets, manuscript drafts, and notes. No final manuscript is present.
  - Craig Ranch Study, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 42)
- Technical Committee—Tenure, 26
  Contains notes, and questions and statements on health, nutrition, medical care, size of unit, tenure, labor and migration, credit and taxation, and the conservation and use of forest resources, related to maximizing contributions to the war effort (WWII), special topics, and correspondence.
  - Original Reports (Box 10, Folder 43)
  - Special Individual Topics (Box 10, Folder 44)
- Sinclair Farm Record Analysis, 1923-1939; 27
  - Sinclair Farm Record Analysis, 1923-1939 (Box 10, Folder 45)
- Dairy Study, 1957; 28
  Proffers manuscript, "Dairy Production Alternatives in Western Montana," cost reducing, coding, articles, annual reports, progress reports, news clippings, "It's Your Business! Dairy Production Alternatives for Western Montana," data forms, notes, publications, analyses, dairy farm locations, land size and tenure, dairy size and type, labor, crop system, livestock system, other income, power, machines, equipment, farm expenses, husbandry, pasture management, breeding practices and cow replacement, dairy expenses, milk handling, dairy marketing, district maps, irrigation.
  - "Dairy Production Alternatives in Western Montana", 1957 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Dairy Study—Development of Coding Systems (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Dairy Study—Annual Report on Research, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Dairy Study—Code Sheets I-IV / Budget Forms (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Dairy Study—Articles (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Dairy Study—Notes on Progress Report, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Dairy Study—News Releases (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Dairy Study—Alternatives for Cream Producers (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Dairy Study—Field Information, Sanders & Missoula Co. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Dairy Study—Field Data, Ravalli Co. (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Dairy Study—Field Data, Lake Co. (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Dairy Study—Field Data, Flathead Co. (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Dairy Study—Notes & Tabulation Data, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Dairy Study—IBM Analysis (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Dairy Study—Publications, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Dairy Study—Organizational Alternatives on Dairy Farms in Western Mountain Valleys (proposed), project statement and correspondence (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Dairy Study—Production Alternatives on Dairy Farms in Western Montana (data forms) (Box 11, Folder 17-18)
  - Dairy Study—Ravalli Co. Marketings 0. Dairy Study—Lake Co. Marketings (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Dairy Study—Production Alternatives on Dairy Farms in Western Montana (data forms)- Ravalli Co. (Box 11, Folder 21-22)
  - Dairy Study—Preliminary Analysis & Notes (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Dairy Study—Production Alternatives on Dairy Farms in Western Montana (data forms)—Lake Co. (Box 11, Folder 24-26)
  - Dairy Study—Tabulation Sheets, Lake Co. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Dairy Study—Production Alternatives on Dairy Farms in Western Montana (data forms)- Ravalli Co. (Box 12, Folder 2-4)
  - Dairy Study—Tabulation Sheets, Ravalli Co. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Dairy Study—Ravalli Co. Marketings (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Dairy Study (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Dairy Study—Lake Co. Marketing (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Dairy Study—Soil Depleting and Conserving Crops (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Dairy Study—Tabulation Sheets, Flathead Co. (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Dairy Study—AAA District Maps (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Dairy Study—Drought Maps (two maps removed for oversize storage; see curator for info) (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Dairy Study—Schedules (Box 12, Folder 13-15)
  - Dairy Study—Production Alternatives on Dairy Farms in Western Montana (data forms)- Flathead Co (Box 12, Folder 16-20)
  - Dairy Study—Farm Facts, 1953-1955 (Box 12, Folder 21)
- Cooperative Farm Management Study—Agricultural Economics Dept. and BAE, 29
  Study conducted by the Montana State College Agricultural Economics Department and the U.S. Bureau of Agricultural Economics. Gives operator names and locations of property, irrigation districts in Bitterroot Valley, buildings, machinery and equipment, livestock, tillage practices, map of farm with fields and crops, crops grown, irrigation, fertilization practices, labor, farm cost data, and farm income.
  - Cooperative Farm Management Study (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Bitterroot Drainage Material (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Cooperative Farm Management Study (Box 13, Folder 3-5)
- Beaverhead County Survey, 1919; 30
  This series provides data from a survey of communities in Beaverhead County in 1919, including a summary sheet, community name, community dimensions, topography, post office names, number of rural routes and starting points, natural resources, chief income sources, irrigation, dry farming, tenants, owners, other industries and persons employed, relationship between businessmen and farmers, population in villages and open country, means of communication, community leadership, important institutions and organizations, newspapers, public libraries, social classes, community activities, social organizations and social life, church surveys with location, denominations, ministers, equipment, church floor plans, finance, membership numbers and occupations, meetings, parish, names of other white and negro churches, foreign population, Sunday school, other church organizations, special work, Jackson community photograph, and a two-page handwritten commentary on the survey.
  - Beaverhead County Survey (Map removed for oversize storage), 1919 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Wibaux County Survey, 1919-1920; 31
  Includes county summary, county name, population, other races and nationalities.
  - Wibaux County Survey, 1919-1920 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Photographs (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Successful Farms, 1921; 32
  According to the inventory listing for this accession, this series may be part of Wilson's Triangle Study. Includes "Farm Survey Record" forms from the Montana Agricultural Experiment Station Department of Farm Management which provide information on the county, operator of farm, addresses, acres owned and rented, acres in various uses, crop records, livestock records and products, other income sources, feed and seed inventories, current expenses, machinery and equipment, real estate, farm finance, unpaid labor, and notes. Counties include Ravalli, Flathead, Yellowstone, Hill, Pondera, Liberty, Toole, Chouteau, Teton, Cascade, and Glacier. Forms for the cost of milk production provide data on grain fed and raised during the year, grain purchased during the year, pasture, buildings, insurance, veterinary, forage raised and fed during the year, forage purchased during the year, labor on cows, and products from cows. Counties represented include Ravalli, Yellowstone, and Flathead.
  - Successful Farms, 1921 (Box 13, Folder 9-14)
- State Farmer Loans, 33
  Provides information on state lands. Materials are arranged by county. Offers data concerning location, acres granted, patent, lands sold, easements and rights of way, and acreage retained by state. No report for this study is present.
  - State Farmer Loans (Box 13, Folder 14-19)
- Farm Real Estate Mortgage and Foreclosure Study, 1911-1938; 34
  This study appears to have been conducted at the behest of the Federal Government, and covers the period between 1911 and 1938. According to a cover letter in one of the files, the compiler was H.V. Brown. The data for this study appears to have been gathered in 16 Montana counties, which were then used to present a state average. There is no final report with this series, although the USDA Farm Mortgage Recordings report for Montana is included.
  - Cover letter and carbon for the initial study requirement. Also includes the "Real Estate Mortgage Summary" for 16 MT counties and other related data (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - 29 tables charting farm foreclosures (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Complete set of copies of items in folder 2 (better condition) (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - USDA Farm Mortgage recordings for Alabama through Nebraska (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - USDA Farm Mortgage recordings - Nevada through Wyoming (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Thesis Material for M.E. Quenemoen, 1952; 35
  This series consists of research materials used by M.E. Quenemoen for his thesis, "Economic aspects of water spreader developments on southeastern Montana ranches," done in 1952 on the subject of waterspreaders. Original research questionnaires, project notes, and other items are contained here. There is no final copy of the thesis but it is available in the Special Collections stacks.
  - Diagram of water spreading system, blank research forms, project outline, and survey trip notes, 1952 June and July (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Eleven completed questionnaires (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Public Welfare reports for Ravalli County, 1930s; 36
  Apparently compiled during the 1930s, these reports cover all people moving into the county since 1930. Information regarding all newcomers' occupations, health, place of origin, marital status, and so on is provided. Tables are extant for the period from May to August, 1939, although the entire 1930s period is covered in terms of arrival dates.
  - Reports (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Tax Delinquency Information, 1930s; 37
  Apparently compiled in the 1930s, this series contains tax delinquency information for properties in both Ravalli and Missoula Counties. It includes lot location maps, lists of operators (farmers?) in Ravalli County, and information regarding both the amount of tax owed and how long the owner has been delinquent. Most are handwritten, and many contain penciled notes. There is no final report with this series, or any real indication of this data's purpose or final use.
  - Numbered lot maps for Ravalli County - possibly incomplete (Box 14, Folder 1-9)
  - Numbered lot maps for Missoula County (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Lists titled "Ravalli County Operators" with notes and a list of grantees between 1921 and 1939., 1921-1939 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Land descriptions. (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Three different lists of delinquencies - none look to be complete (Box 14, Folder 13)
- Breeding Improvement Work, 1928-1935; 38
  This project is dated 1929 in the original inventory, but correspondence extant in the files runs from 1928 through 1935. The basic thrust of this project, which seems to have been coordinated or overseen by Harriet Cushman, was to establish standards and certification for Montana poultry flocks in line with those used by the American Poultry Association. There is much information about certification standards, including some used in Washington State, but no final report.
  - Accreditation correspondence. Includes a sample examination for the post of flock inspector, information about Washington State's program, and handwritten notes about a test flock and other flocks in Montana, 1927, 1928-1931 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Flock inspection records for Custer and Gallatin Counties, 1928 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Flock inspection records for Lewis & Clark, Missoula, Pondera, and Powell Counties, 1928 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Flock inspection records for Sweetgrass and Yellowstone Counties, 1928 (Box 14, Folder 17)
- Farm Account Project, 1925-1929; 39
  This project appears to have been geared toward gathering information about farm management and operations. Saunderson and Gilman are listed as the main authorities for the project, which was conducted in 1929. There is earlier information present, including crop records for 1925 and 1926. Records vary from farm summaries (containing expenses and profits) to complete records that include farm labor sheets and inventories. In the latter cases, cards are also present containing information about the farmer, his family, and any laborers present on the property. There is no final report with this series, or any indication as to the nature of the project itself. The mixed correspondence files seem to deal mostly with letters to county extension officers and are filed by the addressee's last name.
  - Summary listing of farms, circa 1926 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Receipts and expenses for Stout, Daw Bros., Friberger, Spears, McKillop, Jaten, DeVore, Heck, Hendrickson, Neill Bros., Kynett, Mutchler, Ecton, and Riggen, 1928 (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Records for C.O. Stout's farm (Ballantine, MT), 1926 (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Records for H.D. Myrick's farm (Square Butte, MT), 1929 (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Records for Matt Reichmuth's farm (Denton, MT), 1929 (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Records for A. and P. Molendye's farm (Billings, MT), 1929 (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Mixed forms (labor and inventory mostly) from Sherman, Riggen, Heck, Hardin, and Cruikshank farms. (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Records from Antler Land Co., W.C. Brinly, and H.A. Brizzee, 1928 (Box 14, Folder 25)
  - Records from E.J. Burnworth, G. DeWitt, 1928 (Box 14, Folder 26)
  - Records from Z. Ecton, C. Gilchrist, 1928 (Box 14, Folder 27)
  - Records from H. Goldberg, W. Hardin, 1928 (Box 14, Folder 28)
  - Records from C. Heeter, R. Hunbert, J. Johnson, V. Johnson, and a Judith Basin Summary. The Heeter records have photographs removed to the flat file., 1928 (Box 14, Folder 29)
  - Records from V. Long, J. Miller, and A. Molendyk, 1928 (Box 14, Folder 30)
  - Records from O. Nelson, L. Passage, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Records from L. Pharis, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Records from M. Reichmuth, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Records from G. Riggen, W. Ruffcorn, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Records from F. Spears, 1927-1928 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Records from Thulesan Bros., E. Windecker, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Records from W. Vanover, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Records from C. Wilbur, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Completed samples of the project forms (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Mixed correspondence filed under 'A' and 'B', plus something titled "Big Team Dope" and the original file listing. (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Mixed correspondence filed under 'C'. (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Mixed correspondence filed under 'D'. (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Mixed correspondence filed under 'E-J.' There was no 'I'. (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Mixed correspondence filed under 'K-L'. (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Mixed correspondence filed under 'M'. (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Mixed correspondence filed under 'N-P'. (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Mixed correspondence filed under 'R'. (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Mixed correspondence filed under 'S'. (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Mixed correspondence filed under 'T-Z'. (Box 15, Folder 19)
- Saunderson Projects, 1923-1938; 40
  This series contains much information from a number of M.H. Saunderson's projects in the late 1930s. Prominent among them are a 1937-1938 range sheep study, a cooperative grazing document, soil conservation reports, drafts of two undated papers ("Some Questions of Policy in the Use and Management of Public Lands in the Eleven Western States" and "Agricultural Conservation Program from the Viewpoint of the Northwest Livestock Producer"), and a Farm Account Book from Alfred Anderson covering the period from 1923-1930. There is no indication of the purpose of the Anderson book, and no final reports are present for the range sheep study or the cooperative grazing and soil conservation projects. The agricultural conservation materials seem to be mostly from the USDA. Conservation program information tailored for Pondera County is featured, along with some information for Yellowstone County. There is also a Work Progress Authority memo and a copy of a Montana soil conservation law (HB 298) from 1937. The range survey data seems to come from 1937, and includes some cooperative grazing agreements and information.
  - Anderson account book (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Carbon drafts of "Some Questions of Policy in the Use and Management of Public Lands in the Eleven Western States" and "Agricultural Conservation Program from the Viewpoint of the Northwest Livestock Producer" with penciled corrections (Box 15, Folder 21)
  - Memos from the Forest Service regarding range survey and cooperative grazing agreements, 1937 (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - Agricultural Conservation Program information (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous items including WPA memo, county immigration results, and list of leased grazing land in the Ellis belt (Box 15, Folder 24)
- Land Pricing Study, 1957; 41
  No final report for this study is contained in these records. The study seems to have been based on land sales conducted during June of 1957, although there are some earlier samples included in the voided surveys files. The study consisted of four types of interviews (Bidder, Buyer, Dealer, and Seller) conducted for land sales. The interview sheets are color-coded and further identified by county and a numeric code for each parcel of land sold. Most of the interviews were conducted by Paul Pilati, W. Rehberg, H. Walton, or Laurence (no initial was given for Laurence, which may be a first or last name). This series is organized by interview type, followed by county and then sale number. Not all the interviews are present in these records, as there are gaps between many of the numbers. A final file contains a copy of the "instructions for enumerators," a blank survey form, and notes covering three counties (Custer, Roosevelt, and Cascade) not included in the interviews. There is also an owners' survey for Golden Valley. Interview series marked with an asterisk are incomplete. The purpose of this study seems to have been to collect data regarding the price of land, reasons for buying and selling, and some occupational information about those involved.
  - Bidder interviews for Fallon and Judith Basin counties (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - Bidder interviews for Wibaux and Yellowstone counties (Box 15, Folder 26)
  - Buyer interviews for Fallon County (1-8) (Box 15, Folder 27)
  - Buyer interviews for Fallon County (9B-16) (Box 15, Folder 28)
  - Buyer interviews for Fallon County (17-26)* (Box 15, Folder 29)
  - Buyer interviews for Judith Basin County (J1-J10)* (Box 15, Folder 30)
  - Buyer interviews for Judith Basin County (J11-J26)* (Box 15, Folder 31)
  - Buyer interviews for Prairie (1) and Wibaux (2-13)* counties (Box 15, Folder 32)
  - Buyer interviews for Wibaux County (14-21B)* (Box 15, Folder 33)
  - Buyer interviews for Yellowstone County (103-115)* (Box 15, Folder 34)
  - Buyer interviews for Yellowstone County (116-136)* (Box 15, Folder 35)
  - Buyer interviews for Yellowstone County (137-147)* (Box 15, Folder 36)
  - Buyer interviews for Yellowstone County (150-163)* (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Buyer interviews for Yellowstone County (164-179)* (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Buyer interviews for Yellowstone County (181-197)* (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Buyer interviews for Yellowstone County (198-204)* (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Dealer interviews for Judith Basin (7-17)* and Wibaux (19)* counties (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Dealer interviews for Yellowstone County (113-204)* (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Seller interviews for Fallon County (1-24)* (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Seller interviews for Judith Basin County (1-27)* (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Seller interviews for Wibaux County (1-21)* (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Seller interviews for Yellowstone County (104-146)* (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Seller interviews for Yellowstone County (147-157)* (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Seller interviews for Yellowstone County (164-173)* (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Seller interviews for Yellowstone County (176-203)* (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Voided buyer interviews (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Voided buyer interviews (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Voided seller interviews (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Voided seller interviews (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous file - includes evaluator instructions and material for counties that do not have interviews included in this Series (Box 16, Folder 18)
- Farm Labor, 1942; 42
  No final report or contextual documentation is included with this series. It consists of a number of questionnaires developed to record farm information (including labor, crops and livestock raised, hiring plans and preferences, information about the farm families, and so on) from 1941 and into 1942. The interviews were conducted during the summer of 1942 on around 300 Montana farms in a number of counties. The forms are numbered (except those marked for discard), but there appears to be no method for the numbering process. Questions on the forms include number of laborers, hiring preferences of the farmer (based on gender, town/vs farm origin, age, and racial groupings), available housing, use of employment service, labor statistics for workers and family members, crops/livestock raised during the study's period, location of the farm and its acreage, and so on. Labor figures and "Crop War Units" and "LWU's" are totaled on the accepted forms in colored pencil, but the series gives no indication as to the meaning of these markings. A set of interviewer instructions, a blank and completed example form, and a number of rejected forms are also included. Forms are rejected based on either the farmer's not farming in 1941 or incomplete entries (most often in the labor sections). The numeric system of the accepted forms has been preserved in this series.
  - Instructions, sample forms, etc. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Forms 1-275 (missing 16,28,31,32,43,64,68,73) (Box 17, Folder 2-34)
  - Disqualified forms - not on farm, 1941 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Disqualified forms - incomplete information (Box 18, Folder 2-7)
- Farm Tax Data, 43